<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Octopress | SIRHOE CODE]]></title>
  <link href="http://sirhoe.github.io/blog/categories/octopress/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://sirhoe.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-28T16:27:58+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://sirhoe.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sir Hoe]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adding Bitbucket Aside to Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://sirhoe.github.io/blog/2014/08/28/adding-bitbucket-aside-to-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-28T12:37:46+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://sirhoe.github.io/blog/2014/08/28/adding-bitbucket-aside-to-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Default Octopress installation came with github support, as a widget-like plugin called &lsquo;aside&rsquo;. The aside plugin will list your github repositores based on the account name you configured in Octopress&rsquo;s <em>_config.xml</em>.</p>

<p>Now I needed another one for Bitbucket and luckily I found <a href="https://github.com/izacus/octopress-bitbucket">plugin developed by Izacus</a>. The installation steps are clear and direct but the resulted Aside was ugly because it didnt include the necessary HTML <em>class</em> tag for my bootstrap css theme to work. Not a big deal, I got it fixed and the last thing I am going to do is contribute the changes back to the project. If you installed the plugin and faced similar issue, feel free to clone from my fork while the <a href="https://github.com/izacus/octopress-bitbucket/pull/3">pull request</a> is pending review.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building a Blog With Static Pages]]></title>
    <link href="http://sirhoe.github.io/blog/2014/08/26/building-a-blog-with%20static-pages/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-26T15:45:13+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://sirhoe.github.io/blog/2014/08/26/building-a-blog-with static-pages</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently, I was looking to start a portfolio site to present my development work. I was contemplated to use the usual <a href="http://www.wordpress.com">Wordpress</a> blogging platform until I found out about the whole static page thing with <a href="http://www.octopress.org">Octopress</a> via <a href="http://pages.github.com">Github Pages</a>. Imagine your blog being versioned in a rock solid SVN such as github and hosted free, I am sold.</p>

<!--more-->


<h1>What is Octopress?</h1>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/octopress.png" title="&lsquo;Octopress Logo&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>In its own words, Octopress is a blogging platform for hackers. Basically that means you will need to be a geek to know how to set it up. Challenge accepted!</p>

<p>Follow the <a href="http://octopress.org/docs/setup/">setup instruction here</a> to get it up and running. Generally, getting it to work in OSX is much easier than Windows due to OSX&rsquo;s underlying unix architecture. After that it is all about wrtting your post in Markdown syntax to have it generated and deployed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
